<?xml version="1.0"?>
	<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	 <channel>
		<title>Phoronix</title>
		<link>https://www.phoronix.com/</link>
		<description>Linux Hardware Reviews, Performance Benchmarks &amp; Open-Source / Free Software News</description>
		<language>en-us</language>
	  <item>
   <title>Shotcut Video Editor Now Using Hardware Decoding By Default Except For NVIDIA On Linux</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Shotcut-26.1-Video-Editor</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Shotcut-26.1-Video-Editor</guid>
   <description>Shotcut 26.1 is now available as the latest  feature update to this open-source and cross-platform video editing solution. Shotcut 26.1 is finally defaulting to GPU hardware accelerated video decoding by default for all platforms sans NVIDIA GPUs on Linux...</description>
   <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 16:11:45 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Phosh Mobile Phone UI Making Progress On GTK4 Port</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Phosh-GTK4-Progress</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Phosh-GTK4-Progress</guid>
   <description>Evangelos Ribeiro Tzaras presented today at FOSDEM on the latest work around Phosh, the mobile phone user interface / Wayland shell project for mobile Linux environments. Phosh has been making steady progress and has more features out on the horizon...</description>
   <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 14:52:18 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Budgie 10.10.1 Released With Better Stability &amp; Improved Labwc Integration</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Budgie-10.10.1</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Budgie-10.10.1</guid>
   <description>Following the Budgie 10.10 release from earlier this month, Budgie 10.10.1 is now here for closing out January...</description>
   <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 13:56:25 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Linuxulator-Steam-Utils To Enjoy Steam Play Gaming On FreeBSD &amp; Other Options</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/FreeBSD-Gaming-2026</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/FreeBSD-Gaming-2026</guid>
   <description>Presented today at FOSDEM in Brussels was the state of gaming on FreeBSD by Thibault Payet. Besides various open-source games able to be compiled natively for FreeBSD, this BSD can get in on the Steam Play gaming scene thanks to the "linuxulator-steam-utils" project as a set of workarounds for the Steam Linux client on FreeBSD 14 and newer. Linuxulator-steam-utils builds off FreeBSD's Linuxulator support for running Linux binaries to enjoy the likes of Steam and even Steam Play (Proton) Windows games running on this translation layer for Linux and in turn running on FreeBSD...</description>
   <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 12:36:53 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GNOME 50 Is No Longer Treating Variable Rate Refresh &quot;VRR&quot; As Experimental</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/GNOME-50-VRR-Not-Experimental</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/GNOME-50-VRR-Not-Experimental</guid>
   <description>Another great albeit overdue improvement for GNOME 50 has landed: Variable Rate Refresh "VRR" functionality for modern displays is now promoted and no longer treated as an experimental feature...</description>
   <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 06:37:00 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Plasma 6.7 Restoring The Air Plasma Theme, Fixes KWin Issue With Intense Alt+Tab&#039;ing</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/KDE-Brings-Back-Air-Theme</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/KDE-Brings-Back-Air-Theme</guid>
   <description>KDE Plasma developers remain quite busy preparing for the Plasma 6.6 desktop release coming up in a little more than two weeks while at the same time continuing to land early features for the Plasma 6.7 release coming later in the year...</description>
   <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 06:21:09 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>The Last Of The Dolby Digital Plus &quot;E-AC3&quot; Patents Might Now Be Expired</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Dolby-Digital-Plus-E-AC3-2026</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Dolby-Digital-Plus-E-AC3-2026</guid>
   <description>For those interested in the Dolby Digital Plus "Enhanced AC-3" audio compression format for open-source software, the last of the patents for this widely-used format by streaming services and more appears to have expired...</description>
   <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 06:09:24 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GTK Developers Plot Improvements To Tackle This Year - Possible Opt-In Unstable API</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/GTK-2026-Planning-FOSDEM</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/GTK-2026-Planning-FOSDEM</guid>
   <description>GNOME developers had a busy week in preparing for the GNOME 50 beta release, many GNOME developers attending FOSDEM this weekend in Brussels, and other happenings...</description>
   <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2026 05:55:04 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AI Code Review Prompts Initiative Making Progress For The Linux Kernel</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/AI-Code-Review-Prompts-Linux</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/AI-Code-Review-Prompts-Linux</guid>
   <description>Chris Mason, the longtime Linux kernel developer most known for being the creator of Btrfs, has been working on a Git repository with AI review prompts he has been working on for LLM-assisted code review of Linux kernel patches. This initiative has been happening for some weeks now while the latest work was posted today for comments...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 15:55:28 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Ubuntu 26.04 Resolute Snapshot 3 Released For Testing</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Ubuntu-26.04-Snapshot-3</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Ubuntu-26.04-Snapshot-3</guid>
   <description>Resolute Snapshot 3 is now available as the newest monthly test candidate leading up the Ubuntu 26.04 LTS release in April...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 13:25:34 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Ubuntu 26.04 LTS Still Committed To Linux 6.20~7.0 Even If Not Finalized For Release Time</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Ubuntu-26.04-LTS-Linux-Commit</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Ubuntu-26.04-LTS-Linux-Commit</guid>
   <description>Last year Canonical committed to shipping the latest upstream Linux kernel versions in new Ubuntu releases compared to their more conservative choices in prior releases that didn't always align nicely for the latest Linux kernel upstream. Back in December they confirmed Ubuntu 26.04 plans for Linux 6.20~7.0 and their plans remain that way, even if it means the stable Linux 6.20~7.0 stable release won't be officially out quite in time for the initial ISO release...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 12:23:00 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>RISC-V User-Space Control Flow Integrity / Shadow Stack Appears Finally Ready</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/RISC-V-User-Space-CFI</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/RISC-V-User-Space-CFI</guid>
   <description>Similar to what has been available on Intel and AMD processors for users with the shadow stack for control-flow integrity, Linux on RISC-V is finally ready to roll-out its user-space control-flow integrity support...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 11:57:16 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Vulkan 1.4.342 Published With Cooperative Matrix Conversion Extension</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Vulkan-1.4.342-Released</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Vulkan-1.4.342-Released</guid>
   <description>Following last week's Vulkan spec updates that brought descriptor heaps and other notable new extensions and the Vulkan Roadmap 2026 Milestone, Vulkan 1.4.342 was published this morning as the latest routine spec update plus one new extension...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 11:02:56 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AMD EPYC 9755 Delivers Decisive Performance Leadership Over Xeon 6 Granite Rapids With Nearly 500 Benchmarks</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/review/amd-epyc-intel-xeon-500</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/review/amd-epyc-intel-xeon-500</guid>
   <description>Back in December I carried out some fresh benchmarks of the Intel Xeon 6980P vs. AMD EPYC 9755 for these competing 128 core server processors using the latest Linux software stack before closing out 2025. That was done with nearly 200 benchmarks and the AMD EPYC Turin Zen 5 processor delivered terrific performance as we have come to enjoy out of the 5th Gen EPYC line-up over the past year and several months. Since then I have ratcheted up the benchmarks with nearly 500 benchmarks between the AMD EPYC 9755 and Intel Xeon 6980P processors for an even more comprehensive look at these CPUs atop Linux 6.18 LTS.</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 10:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Linux&#039;s ublk Adding Batch I/O Dispatch Capability For Greater Performance</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-ublk-Batch-IO-Dispatch</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-ublk-Batch-IO-Dispatch</guid>
   <description>Linux's user-space block device driver framework "ublk" for implementing virtual block device drivers in user-space relayed by IO_uring is introducing batch I/O dispatch infrastructure...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 09:00:25 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>AerynOS Establishes Policy Against LLM Contributions, 2026.01 ISO Refresh</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/AerynOS-2026.01</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/AerynOS-2026.01</guid>
   <description>In kicking off 2026, AerynOS developers have continued to make progress on their build tooling and infrastructure for this Linux distribution formerly known as Serpent OS. They have also been working on a new website design and other updated branding to start the new year...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 08:13:57 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Open-Source Nova Driver In Linux 7.0 Continues Preparing For NVIDIA Turing GPU Support</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Rust-DRM-For-Linux-7.0</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Rust-DRM-For-Linux-7.0</guid>
   <description>This week the Rust DRM changes intended for the Linux 7.0 merge window were sent out by Danilo Krummrich. The Apple Silicon Asahi Linux "AGX" DRM kernel driver still isn't positioned for upstreaming to the mainline kernel so that leaves most of the Rust DRM upstream work currently around the NVIDIA Nova driver as well as the Arm Mali Tyr drivers...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 06:15:02 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Intel Xe Linux Driver Updated To Disable GuC Power DCC For Panther Lake</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Intel-Disabling-DCC-PTL</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Intel-Disabling-DCC-PTL</guid>
   <description>Queued up in DRM-Next for the Intel open-source graphics driver ahead of the Linux 7.0 kernel cycle is expanding GPU temperature sensor reporting, multi-device SVM prep, multi-queue support for Crescent Island, Nova Lake display support, and other feature work. With the Linux 6.19 stable release fast approaching, DRM-Next is now focusing in on reading early fixes with concluding feature activity for this next merge window...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 05:53:20 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Intel Releases LLM-Scaler-vLLM 1.3 With New LLM Model Support</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Intel-LLM-Scaler-vLLM-1.3</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Intel-LLM-Scaler-vLLM-1.3</guid>
   <description>Intel today released the LLM-Scaler-vLLM 1.3 update with expanding the array of large language models that can run on Intel Arc Battlemage graphics cards with this Docker-based stack for deploying vLLM...</description>
   <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 05:34:16 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Microsoft Working On Improved vCPU Scheduler Support For Hyper-V Linux VMs</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Hyper-V-Integrated-Scheduler</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Hyper-V-Integrated-Scheduler</guid>
   <description>Microsoft posted a patch series for introducing Hyper-V integrated scheduler support into the Linux kernel for enhancing vCPU scheduling behavior for virtual machines running within Microsoft's virtualized environment...</description>
   <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 17:47:31 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>DDR5-4800 vs. DDR5-6000 Performance With The AMD Ryzen 7 9850X3D In 300+ Benchmarks</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/review/amd-ryzen-7-9850x3d-ddr5</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/review/amd-ryzen-7-9850x3d-ddr5</guid>
   <description>With the incredible market demand around DDR5 memory and significantly elevated pricing on the more premium DDR5 memory modules, as part of the AMD Ryzen 7 9850X3D launch there&#039;s been some communication that thanks to 2nd Gen AMD 3D V-Cache, using lower memory speeds like DDR5-4800 can be suitable without much of an impact to the gaming performance. But what about for Linux gaming? And other workloads with the Ryzen 7 9850X3D? Complementing yesterday&#039;s Linux review of the Ryzen 7 9850X3D are benchmarks of DDR5-4800 vs. DDR5-6000 performance with Ubuntu Linux and this new 3D V-Cache 8-core / 16-thread desktop processor.</description>
   <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 12:50:00 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Libcamera 0.7 Released - GPU Acceleration Support For SoftISP Can Deliver 15x Performance</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/libcamera-0.7</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/libcamera-0.7</guid>
   <description>Libcamera 0.7 was published today for this modern software library for image signal processors (ISPs) and embedded cameras under Linux. The standout change with libcamera 0.7 is initial plumbing for GPU acceleration in the software ISP "SoftISP" for delivering better performance than just CPU-based...</description>
   <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 11:51:00 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>IO_uring Zero-Copy Large Receive Buffer Support To Provide A Nice Performance Win</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/IO-uring-zcrx-Large-RX</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/IO-uring-zcrx-Large-RX</guid>
   <description>Slated for introduction in the next kernel cycle (Linux 6.20~7.0) is introducing large receive buffer support for IO_uring's zero-copy receive code path. This large receive buffer support can be very beneficial for those with higher-end networking hardware capable of handling the larger buffers for some significant performance and efficiency wins...</description>
   <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 11:21:15 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Libgcrypt 1.12 Released With VAES/AVX-512 Accelerated AES: 2x Performance On AMD Zen 5</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/libgcrypt-1.12</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/libgcrypt-1.12</guid>
   <description>Werner Koch released libgcrypt 1.12 as the newest feature release to this library providing the cryptographic building blocks used by GnuPG and other software like email clients, file encryption utilities, and other software...</description>
   <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 09:39:14 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>NVIDIA GeForce NOW Is Now Available Natively On Linux In Flatpak Form</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/review/nvidia-geforce-now-linux</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/review/nvidia-geforce-now-linux</guid>
   <description>Following NVIDIA&#039;s announcement back at CES of their GeForce NOW game streaming service coming to Linux as a native desktop application, today&#039;s the day. The GeForce NOW Linux-native build is being published and the review embargo has lifted.</description>
   <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 09:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Valve Developer Improves Aging AMD APUs On Linux With VRR, DP/HDMI Audio, HDR &amp; Atomic</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/AMDGPU-DC-Improved-GCN-1.1-APUs</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/AMDGPU-DC-Improved-GCN-1.1-APUs</guid>
   <description>Timur Kristóf of Valve's Linux graphics team last year addressed remaining issues in the open-source AMDGPU kernel graphics driver so old AMD GCN 1.0 and GCN 1.1 GPUs could transition to using AMDGPU by default rather than the former "Radeon" kernel driver that is largely in maintenance mode for pre-GCN/RDNA GPUs. One caveat though was the GCN 1.1 APU support still having some limitations leading to Kaveri and friends not being able to use the modern AMDGPU DC "Display Core" code. But new patches from Timur take care of those limitations...</description>
   <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 06:36:50 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Intel Thermal Daemon 2.5.11 Released With Wildcat Lake Support</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Intel-Thermal-Daemon-2.5.11</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Intel-Thermal-Daemon-2.5.11</guid>
   <description>With Intel Panther Lake now shipping, open-source Intel engineers working on the client side are turning to tidying up support for their next target: Wildcat Lake. That more cost effective alternative to Panther Lake now has Intel Thermal Daemon support in getting ready for Linux desktops/laptops...</description>
   <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 06:19:48 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>NVIDIA VA-API Driver 0.0.15 Released With A Few Fixes</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/NVIDIA-VA-API-Driver-0.0.15</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/NVIDIA-VA-API-Driver-0.0.15</guid>
   <description>The NVIDIA-VAAPI-Driver 0.0.15 was released overnight as this VA-API driver implementation built atop NVIDIA's NVDEC interface used by their proprietary user-space driver stack. The purpose of NVIDIA-VAAPI-Driver as this community open-source project continues to be around enabling video acceleration for NVIDIA GPUs with the Firefox web browser on Linux that supports the VA-API interface but not NVIDIA's NVDEC...</description>
   <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 05:57:40 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GNU gettext Reaches Version 1.0 After 30+ Years In Development - Adds LLM Features</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/GNU-gettext-1.0</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/GNU-gettext-1.0</guid>
   <description>Sun Microsystems began developing gettext in the early 1990s and the GNU Project began GNU gettext development in 1995 for this widely-used internationalization and localization system commonly for multi-lingual integration. While GNU gettext is commonly used by countless open-source projects and adapted for many different programming languages, only an hour ago was GNU gettext 1.0 finally released...</description>
   <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:31:08 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Wasmer 7.0 Released For Advancing WebAssembly On The Desktop &amp; Anywhere</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Wasmer-7.0-Released</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Wasmer-7.0-Released</guid>
   <description>Wasmer 7.0 is out today for this WebAssembly "WASM" run-time for enabling lightweight containers that can run "anywhere" from the desktop to cloud and the edge.  The security-minded and extensible WASM runtime provided by Wasmer has already proven to be quite robust while with Wasmer 7.0 has become even more featureful...</description>
   <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 16:13:02 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>GNOME 50 Finally Lands Improved Discrete GPU Detection</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/GNOME-50-Better-GPU-Detection</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/GNOME-50-Better-GPU-Detection</guid>
   <description>The upcoming release of GNOME 50 to be found in the likes of Ubuntu 26.04 LTS and Fedora Workstation 44 will feature improved discrete GPU detection within the GNOME Shell. This effort has been two years coming and finally merged this week...</description>
   <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 15:45:11 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
  <item>
   <title>Mesa 26.0-rc2 Released With Numerous AMD, NVIDIA &amp; Intel Driver Fixes</title>
   <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Mesa-26.0-rc2-Released</link>
   <guid>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Mesa-26.0-rc2-Released</guid>
   <description>Following last week's code branching / feature freeze and first release candidate of Mesa 26.0, Mesa 26.0-rc2 is now available with an initial batch of bug fixes for this quarter's feature update to these open-source OpenGL and Vulkan drivers...</description>
   <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 13:03:07 -0500</pubDate>
   <dc:creator>Michael Larabel</dc:creator>
  </item>
</channel>
	</rss>